Finding Aid for Pun Plamondon papers, 1968-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pun Plamondon Papers 1968-2003, 1968-1973, 1982-1983
Plamondon, Pun.
4 linear feet
2014095 Aa 2
Papers of Pun Plamondon, activist, writer, and journalist who in 1968 co-founded the White Panther Party with John Sinclair. Papers include material related to Plamondon's political activism in the late 1960s-early 1970s, material related to the White Panthers Party, the Rainbow People's Party, and Plamondon's relationship with John Sinclair, as wells as material related to law suits against Plamondon and his trials, most notably United States v. U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, et al. and the State of Michigan v. Craig Blazier and Lawrence R. (Pun) Plamondon. Also material related to his autobiographical writings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Pun Plamondon (donor no. 11113 ) in May 2014.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Pun Plamondon was born in Traverse City, Mich. in 1945 to a part-Ojibway mother and half-Ottawa father. He was adopted by a Caucasian couple, the Plamondons, who named him Lawrence Robert. Plamondon was not aware of his Native American roots until he was 16 years old. Plamondon attended Catholic schools, then spend some time on the East Coast before returning to Michigan in 1965. That summer he got a job as a union organizer of migrant farm workers with the American Federation of Labor/Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL/CIO), traveling throughout the Midwest. At the same time Plamondon took to heavy drinking and drug use.
With a group of friends Plamondon settled in Flint for a short while, drinking alcohol and "jumping through welfare hoops," by his own admission. In 1967 he arrived in Detroit, settling in on Plum Street, a hippie enclave near Tiger Stadium. There he got a job making sandals and accessories. At some point in 1967 Plamondon met John Sinclair who at the time edited and wrote for the 24-page The Sun, a publication that "brought together a new cultural content in the highest artistic form." Soon he started spending time with Sinclair, journalist Peter Werbe and artist Gary Grimshaw, who were running two underground newspapers, the Detroit Sun and the Fifth Estate.
In the 1968 the group moved to Ann Arbor, Mich. where they established a commune. Shortly after Plamondon became inspired by an interview given by Huey P. Newton, cofounder of the Black Panther Party, in which Newton suggested that in order to support the Black Panthers "[the white people] can form a White Panther Party." At this point Plamondon was becoming more political, and more militant. Plamondon and Sinclair modeled the White Panther Party after the Black Panthers, fighting for a clean planet and the freeing of political prisoners. The White Panthers went further, advocating rock 'n' roll, dope, sex in the streets and an end to capitalism. The ten-point program of the White Panther Party demanded economic and cultural freedom. "Everything free for everybody!" and a total "assault" on the culture by any means necessary were the essence of the White Panther program. Plamondon, the White Panther Party's Minister of Defense, took on the affectations of a revolutionary, donning a black motorcycle jacket and a swaggering attitude.
In October 1968 Plamondon and Sinclair were indicted for bombing a CIA office in Ann Arbor on September 28, 1968. No one was injured in the blast. The bombing was one of the eight anti-establishment bombings that had occurred in the Detroit area at the time. A sealed indictment was returned by a grand jury on October 7, 1969. The named defendants were Sinclair, Plamondon, and John Waterhouse "Jack" Forrest, the White Panther Party Minister of Education for Detroit.
Changing his appearance by cutting shoulder-length hair short and shaving off his beard, he went underground for 11 months, traveling between San Francisco, Seattle, New York, Toronto, Germany, Italy, and Algeria. In May 1969, at the age of 24, he made the FBI's 10 Most Wanted list. In July 1970 he went back to Michigan. Plamondon and "Skip" Taube, also a White Panther, were stopped for littering near St. Ignace. Thus Plamondon was discovered, arrested, and spent 32 months in federal prison waiting for his trial.
Sinclair, Forrest and Plamondon were charged with conspiracy to destroy government property, with Plamondon also charged with the dynamite bombing of the CIA office. The government attorneys involved in the prosecution were Ralph B. Guy, J. Kenneth Lowrie, and John H. Hausner. Plamondon and Sinclair were represented by Leonard I. Wineglass and William Kunstler. Hugh M. Davis, a lawyer with the National Lawyers Guild Detroit chapter represented Forrest. Judge Damon J. Keith presided over the case. During proceedings, federal government officials admitted to wiretapping Plamondon's conversations without a warrant. During his trial, U.S. District Judge Damon Keith ordered that the government release the tapes, but the prosecution refused. The case went to the U.S. Supreme Court. United States v. U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, et al. case, also known as the Keith Case, resulted in a unanimous 8-0 ruling, the requirements of the Fourth Amendment in cases of domestic surveillance targeting a domestic threat. The Supreme Court upheld the prior rulings in the case, holding that the wiretaps were an unconstitutional violation of the Fourth Amendment and as such must be disclosed to the defense. This established the precedent that a warrant needed to be obtained before beginning electronic surveillance even if domestic security issues were involved.
Plamondon returned to Ann Arbor to join Sinclair who himself was released on bond while appeals were heard. The cumulative effects of the imprisonment had marked the end of the White Panther Party in Michigan, which renamed itself the Rainbow People's Party while Sinclair and Plamondon were in prison, before disbanding in 1973.
Early in 1972, Sinclair founded (with Peter Andrews) the Rainbow Multi-Media Corporation, serving as its vice-president and creative director. A Michigan non-profit organization, Rainbow Multi-Media (RMM) was designed as an alternative music-business company with a community-service orientation. To further its ultimate goal of restructuring the music industry and the entire society as well along cooperative, creative and communalistic lines, the company made its resources available on a cost-or-less basis to community organizations committed to progressive social change.
In July 1973 Plamondon and Craig Blazier, the Rainbow People's Party member, were arrested on the charge of conspiracy, extortion, armed robbery, and criminal usury. The case involved a sale of $3,000 worth of marijuana by Plamondon and Blazier to a Traverse City drug dealer Uwe Wagner. When Wagner refused to failed to pay, Plamondon and Blazier then threaten to expose Wagner as a drug dealer in the Ann Arbor Sun. Despite numerous contradictions in the State's case, Plamondon and Blazier were bound for a trial and their bond was set at $100,000. It took 30 days and three bond hearings, before the judge reduced the bonds to $5,000 for Blazier and $25,000 for Plamondon. Blazier was bonded out but it took 25 days, two rock-n'-roll benefits, and two more hearings before Plamondon's bond was reduced to $10,000. The Rainbow People's Party organized Plamondon and Blazier defense campaign. During the trial the prosecution used as evidence taped telephone conversations between Wagner and the defendants in which the threats were made. The phone calls were made by Wagner on request of the police and no search warrant was ever obtained. In July 1973 all charges were dropped, except one: extortion by threat of accusation. Blazier received 3 years of probation while Plamondon received a 5-year probation sentence. In 1975 he State Court of Appeals reversed the 1973 extortion conviction, stating that the taped conversations admitted as evidence violated Plamondon's and Blazier's right against unreasonable search and seizure.
Plamondon found work driving equipment trucks for rock bands including Kiss and Foreigner, and for Bob Seger. During this period Plamondon was drinking heavily and used cocaine and other drugs. After several lost years, in 1981 he met Louis Sawaquat, an Ottawa Indian who invited him to sit and smoke a traditional pipe of tobacco. That night, Plamondon told his new friend about his Native American heritage and opened up about his troubles with alcohol and drugs. Sawaquat then suggested that Plamondon learned more about his heritage. Plamondon changed his life by stopping drinking, rediscovering his roots, and becoming a respected Odawa tribal elder. In the early 1980s Plamondon began writing an autobiographical novel he called The Outlaw Papers. This resulted in publishing a memoir Lost from the Ottawa: the Story of the Journey Back (Cloverdale, Mich.: Plamondon, Inc., 2004). Also in the early 1980s Plamondon became involved with the Circle Pines Center in Delton, Mich., a non-profit education and recreation center, where he organized summer camp programs for youth. Plamondon continues to work with children by visiting schools, libraries, museums and summer camps telling American Indian stories and leading storytelling workshops.
The Pun Plamondon papers mostly include material related to his political activism in the late 1960s-early 1970s, his trials and imprisonment. The collection is divided into four series: Activism, Legal Files The Outlaw Papers, 1945-1975, and Other Activities.
Subjects:
Blazier, Craig.; Kiss (Musical group); Michigan--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Plamondon, Pun.; Political activists--Michigan.; Prisons--Michigan.; Radicalism--Michigan.; Rainbow Peoples Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Seger, Bob.; Sinclair, John, 1941-; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; White Panther Party.; Wiretapping--Michigan.; Wiretapping--United States.
Genre/Form:
Audiocassettes.
- Activism 1968-1975
  The Activism series (1.2 linear feet) includes material related to Palmondon's activism in the late 1960s through 1975. One will find correspondence, official and ideological statements, meeting notes, flyers, and articles issued by the Human Rights Party, the White Panther Party, the Rainbow People's Party, Michigan Marijuana Initiative, and other activist organizations. Also found here is material related to John Sinclair and other individuals. Of note are copies of Sinclair's correspondence from prison. A number of folders contain materials related to prisons and prisoners' rights. These include correspondence, reports, educational materials, issues of prison publications from around the country, material related to inmates' grievances, as well as poetry by prisoners, and Plamondon's own prison writings and notebook.
  - Belle Isle Love-In (Box 1)
  - End the war (Box 1)
  - Freedom Of Information Act files
    - Bellant, Russell (Box 1)
    - Cahill, David P. (Box 1)
    - Morris, Jon D. (Box 1)
  - Human Rights Party (Box 1)
  - John Sinclair
    - 2nd ward campaign (Box 1)
    - Letters of support (Box 1)
  - Michigan Marijuana Initiative (Box 1)
  - Network, Ann Arbor (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Ann Arbor) (Box 1)
  - Prisons and prisoners
    - Afro-American Cultural Studies (Box 1)
    - Collected publications (Box 1)
    - Inmate assistance programs (Box 1)
    - Lynch, David (Box 1)
    - Mail surveillance (Box 1)
    - Michigan Committee for Prisoners' Rights (Box 1)
    - Milan Correctional Institution (Box 1)
    - New World Culture Studies (Box 1)
    - Pot busts (Box 1)
    - Prison notebooks (Box 1)
    - Prison poetry by others (Box 1)
    - Prison writings by Plamondon (Box 1)
    - Prisoners' Labor Union (Box 1)
  - Rainbow Agency (Box 1)
  - Rainbow Multi Media (Box 1)
  - Robert F. Williams Legal Defense Fund (Box 1)
  - Tribal Council (Box 1)
  - White Panther Party/ Rainbow People's Party
    - Ideology (Box 1)
    - John Sinclair, correspondence from prison (Box 1)
    - Rainbow People's Party Cadre meeting notes (Box 1)
    - Rainbow People's Party meeting notes (Box 1)
    - White Panther Party FBI file (Box 1)
    - South University disorders (Box 1)
  - Collected miscellaneous printed publications
    - Congress of Afrikan People (Box 2)
    - Cuba (Box 2)
    - How has fascism changed? The Fifth Estate discussion paper (Box 2)
    - Latin America (Box 2)
    - Mother Lode (Box 2)
    - North Korea (Box 2)
    - On Repression: a speech by Kenneth Cockrel (Box 2)
    - Organization of the Solidarity of the Peoples of Africa, Asia and Latin America (Box 2)
- Legal Files
  The Legal Files series (2 linear feet) includes materials mostly related to two major trials in which Plamondon appeared as defendant: the 1972 United States v. U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, et al. (or, the "C.I.A. case," as Palmondon refers to it in his papers) and the 1973 State of Michigan v. Craig Blazier and Lawrence R. (Pun) Plamondon. Researchers will find court documents: briefs, motions, petitions, etc., Detroit Red Squad surveillance reports, wiretap logs, and other CIA and FBI material, correspondence, newspaper articles, and material related to legal defense campaign. Also included in the series material related to other lawsuits, most notably John Sinclair's lawsuits against the government officials.
  - United States v. U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, et al., 1972 (the "C.I.A. case")
    - Articles and interviews by Plamondon and by the Defense (Box 2)
    - Biography of Pun Plamondon, by Rainbow People's Party (Box 2)
    - Court documents: briefs, motions, etc., 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Detroit Red Squad
      - Plamondon file (Box 2)
      - Wiretap logs September 1970-January 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan State Police (MSP)
      - 1968-1974, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - General 1969-1970, undated (Box 2)
      - Index to MPS files (Box 2)
    - Federal time fight (Box 3)
    - Freedom Of Information Act files (Box 3)
    - Forrest, Jack (Box 3)
    - Kunstler, William (Box 3)
    - National Lawyers Guild-Detroit chapter correspondence (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings
      - Capture (Box 3)
      - C.I.A. (Box 3)
      - John Sinclair (Box 3)
      - Supreme Court (Box 3)
      - Wiretap (Box 3)
    - Selective Service (Box 3)
    - St. Ignace (Box 3)
    - Taube, "Skip" reduction of sentence (Box 3)
    - Valler, David (Box 3)
    - White Panthers Party statements (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1971-2003 (Box 3)
  - State of Michigan v. Craig Blazier and Lawrence R. (Pun) Plamondon, 1973
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Court documents
      - Appeal (Box 3)
      - Motions, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Oral arguments (Box 3)
      - Preliminary examination (Box 3)
    - Defense files, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - Probation (Box 3)
    - Rainbow People's Party statements (Box 3)
    - Sound recording: Allen Ginsburg discussing FBI methods on David Covett show, March11 1982 (Box 3)
  - Friends of the Rainbow People v. Board of Regents of the University of Michigan 1972 (Box 3)
  - Rainbow lawsuit, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Sinclair, Plamondon, Forrest v. Schriber, 1970-1989; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Sinclair v. Johnson 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Sinclair et al v. Kleindienst, 1969-1983; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - State of Michigan v. Plamondon (various charges) 1978, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Tribal Funding, Inc. v. The City of Ann Arbor, Mich. 1974 (Box 4)
  - Wayne County Jail Inmates v. Wayne County Board of Commissioners 1971 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 175-2000 scattered (Box 4)
- The Outlaw Papers, 1945-1975
  The Outlaw Papers, 1945-1975 series (0.4 linear feet) includes drafts, outlines, biographical sketches, proposals, and correspondence related to Plamondon's unpublished autobiographical novel, dated 1982-1983
  - Biographical sketches (Box 4)
  - Book proposals (Box 4)
  - Chapter notes (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1980-1982 (Box 4)
  - Cover (Box 4)
  - Novel outline (Box 4)
  - Part 1 Lost from the Tribe
    - Chapter 1 Natural Cussedness, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Chapter 2 Looking for an Angry Fix/Summer Bums, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Part 4 Underground/Gimme Shelter
    - Chapter 6 Whip Comes (Box 4)
    - Chapter 7 Only Moments to Go!, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Chapter 8 Pun on the Run (Box 4)
- Other Activities
  The Other Activities series (0.4 linear feet) contains files related to Plamondon's involvement with the Circle Pines Center, a recreational camp in Delton, Mich. These files document the 4-H Challenge Club, activities include administrative and general information about the Center, and material related to establishing the Wilderness Homestead group home. Also in the series is material related to Plamondon's years on the road with rock bands. This material includes Bob Seger and Kiss tour schedules, backstage badges, a promotional Bob Seger photograph dated 1978, and collected business cards.
  - Circle Pine Center 1983-1987
    - 4-H Challenge Club (Box 4)
    - Administrative and general (Box 4)
    - Homestead group home (Box 4)
    - Youth Committee (Box 4)
  - Indian logos and mascots in schools (Box 4)
  - Road files 1976-1979, undated
    - Bob Seger (Box 4)
      (includes a black-and-white promotional photograph)
    - Kiss (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
Related Collections
Bentley Historical Library holds the following related material:
Jeff Gold collection of John Sinclair materials, 1969-1971
John and Leni Sinclair papers, 1957-1979. Finding aid available online
Lost from the Ottawa: the Story of the Journey Back by Pun Plamondon (Cloverdale, Mich.: Plamondon, Inc., 2004). Call number: DB 2 P698 A12.
Music is Revolution (sound recordings)
Twenty to Life: the Life & Times of John Sinclair (video recording)